Guide to the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Male Photographers in the American West
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter Palmquist collection of male photographers in the American west
1840-2003
WA MSS S-2733
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
160.34
(592 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
The collection includes information about and examples of the work of male amateur and commercial photographers, studio assistants, photographic processors, colorists, and photojournalists collected by Peter Palmquist from 1971 until his death in 2003. The collection, which documents the practice and occupation of photography in the American west, circa 1840 to circa 1900, consists of biographical files for more than nine thousand men and businesses, as well as photographs and ancillary materials that represent the work of more than two thousand individuals and firms.
Palmquist, Peter E.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Peter E. Palmquist on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Biographical information and photographic materials related to women photographers active in the American West are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Women in Photography (WA MSS S-2600). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Biographical information and photographic materials related to male photographers active in Humboldt County, California, are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Humboldt County, California, Male Photographers (WA MSS S-2670). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Cased photographs related to male photographers active in the American West are included in the Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection (WA Photos 402). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Books and periodicals formerly in the personal library of Peter Palmquist are accessible via the library catalog by searching special collections for the search string: "Palmquist, Peter E., Ownership."
Peter E. Palmquist (1936-2003)
A photographer, collector, and historian of photography, Peter Eric Palmquist was born in Oakland, California on September 23, 1936. In 1944, he moved with his family to Ferndale, California, and he spent most of his life in Humboldt County. During adolescence, Palmquist trained himself in photography. He served in the United States Army as a photographer from 1955 to 1959, mainly with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe in Paris, France. Palmquist worked briefly as a photographer for the state government of California from 1959 to 1961. From 1961 until his retirement in 1989, Palmquist worked as a staff photographer for Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, where he also graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in Art in 1965.
From 1971 until his death, Palmquist collected textual materials and hundreds of thousands of photographic items documenting the practice and occupation of photography from its beginning through the turn of the twenty-first century. He had particular interests in early California photographers, photographers of the American West, and women photographers.
A self-trained researcher and historian of photography, Palmquist organized more than a hundred exhibitions and wrote more than three hundred articles and a hundred monographs. He was a founding editor of The Daguerreian Annual, and a president of the National Stereoscopic Association.
Palmquist died January 13, 2003, in Oakland.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes information about and examples of the work of male amateur and commercial photographers, studio assistants, photographic processors, colorists, and photojournalists collected by Peter Palmquist from 1971 until his death in 2003. The collection, which documents the practice and occupation of photography in the American West, consists of biographical files for more than nine thousand men and businesses, as well as photographs and ancillary materials that represent the work of more than two thousand individuals and firms. A database [http://brbl-legacy.library.yale.edu/Palmquist_MPAW/] provides name access to biographical files, as well as information regarding their aliases, working locations, life dates, and work dates. Individual photographers represented by significant quantities of material in the collection include Frank C. Aston, Walter T. Fitch, Louis Herman Heller, Thomas Houseworth, Benjamin Franklin Howland, Charles Wallace Jacob Johnson, George Daniels Morse, John Pitcher Spooner, Isaiah West Taber, Robert H. Vance, Carleton E. Watkins, and Chester L. Weed. Firms with substantial groups of material in the collection include Bradley & Rulofson, the Bushnell Photo Company, and The Imperial Studio.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Research Files, 1888-2003. II. Photographic Materials, circa 1840-2003.
Photographers -- Biography; Photographers -- California; Photographers -- West (U.S.); Photography -- Bio-bibliography; Photography -- California; Photography -- West (U.S.); Photography, Artistic; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Biography files; Negatives (photographs); Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Transparencies; Aston, Frank C., 1871-1966; Fitch, Walter T.; Heller, Louis Herman, 1839-1928; Houseworth, Thomas, 1829-1915; Howland, Benjamin Franklin, 1828-1900; Johnson, C. W. J. (Charles Wallace Jacob), 1833-1903; Morse, George Daniels, 1835-; Palmquist, Peter E.; Spooner, John Pitcher; Taber, I. W. (Isaiah West), 1830-1912; Vance, Robert H., 1825-1876; Watkins, Carleton E., 1829-1916; Weed, Chester L.; Bradley & Rulofson; Bushnell Photo Company; Imperial Studio (San Francisco, Calif.)
- Research Files, 1888-2003; Series I; 90.5; (332 boxes)
  Arrangement
  This series is organized into six subseries: Biographical Files, Biographical Index Cards, Biographical Volumes, California Research Volumes, Geographical Research Volumes, and Asian American Photographers Research
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists principally of biographical files and volumes that document over nine thousand men involved with photography in the Trans-Mississippi West from circa 1840 to 2000. The majority of the men documented in the files worked from 1860 to 1920. The series also provides information on photographers in geographically distinct regions, as well as the general field of photography.
  Palmquist and his assistants compiled much of the material from secondary sources between 1971 and 2003.
  - Biographical Files
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by personal or corporate name.
    This portion of the finding aid provides access to boxes containing more than nine thousand individual biographical files. A database [http://brbl-legacy.library.yale.edu/Palmquist_MPAW/] provides individual name access to men and photography studios represented in this subseries, as well as information regarding their aliases, working locations, life dates, and work dates.
    The contents of individual biographical files range from solely the name of a man or photography studio to more comprehensive information, such as his life and work dates, his working locations, as well as professional or personal acquaintances.
    The files are housed in the original letter-size folders used by Palmquist, occasionally supplemented by folders provided by the processing archivist where no folder previously existed or the original folder had deteriorated beyond repair.
    The files provide particularly strong documentation for male photographers in California.
    - A & A Lightning Viewing Company to Asburn (Box 1)
    - Asher, Julius, to Barron, H. J. (Box 2)
    - Barroso to Bilt, August (Box 3)
    - Bingay, to Brewster, J. C. (Box 4)
    - Bricker to Burney, J. W. (Box 5)
    - Burnham, A. C., to Chalmers, James Calder, Jr. (Box 6)
    - Chamberlain, Daniel, to Conyer, James. (Box 7)
    - Cook to Currier, L. W. (Box 8)
    - Curry, Francis A., to Dice, Albert R. (Box 9)
    - Dickenson, John C., to Eckart, W. R. (Box 10)
    - Eckenrode, Harry, to Ferry, Moses F. (Box 11)
    - Fessenden, Benjamin, to Frobus, John H. C. N. (Box 12)
    - Froebe, Th. W., to Goodrum, W. E. (Box 13)
    - Goodsell, C. E., to Hamilton and Starr (Box 14)
    - Hamlin, R. N., to Heaswell, Charles (Box 15)
    - Heath, Charles E., to Hoefler, Paul Louis (Box 16)
    - Hoelke, Hermann E., to Hyder, Edward C. H. (Box 17)
    - Ibarra, Justo, to Johnson, Willis E. (Box 18)
    - Johnston & Bush to Killian, E. J. (Box 19)
    - Kimball, E. H., to Lawhun, Samuel (Box 20)
    - Lawrence to Long, Jack (Box 21)
    - Longaker, Joseph, to Martenet, Jefferson (Box 22)
    - Martin to Mensch, George A. (Box 23)
    - Mentz, John Henry, to Morret, William P. (Box 24)
    - Morrill to Nutt, A. E. (Box 25)
    - Nutting, W. R., to Pearl Art Gallery (Box 26)
    - Pearsall, W. Parish, to Pomeroy, L. E. (Box 27)
    - Pond, C. L., to Rhodes, Joseph (Box 28)
    - Rice to Rundle, N. C. (Box 29)
    - Runnels & Company to Scott, Winfield (Box 30)
    - Scouler, James, to Smetters, S. (Box 31)
    - Smith to Stevenson, Richard (Box 32)
    - Stewart to Tener, Robert E. (Box 33)
    - Tennent, George, to Tyerman, A. G. (Box 34)
    - Tyler and Company, to Warhurst, James E. (Box 35)
    - Warner, Alanson L., to Whitcomb, A. (Box 36)
    - White & Lindsley to Wonacott, H. H. (Box 37)
    - Wood & King to Zynkian, H. K. (Box 38)
  - Biographical Index Cards
    Index cards with brief typescript and manuscript entries and notes created by Palmquist for photographers, photography studios, and publishers, as well as other individuals and groups related to photography in California, Nevada, and Oregon. The index cards include chiefly male photographers, but include some female photographers.
    - California
      - A to B (Box 39)
      - C to F (Box 40)
      - G to L (Box 41)
      - M to R (Box 42)
      - S to Z (Box 43)
    - Nevada (Box 43)
    - Oregon (Box 43)
  - Biographical Volumes
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the surname or corporate name of the photographer or photography studio.
    Under headings for the appropriate photographer or photography studio are volumes compiled by Palmquist and others.
    This subseries chiefly consists of miscellaneous notes and photocopies of secondary material about photographers compiled by Palmquist, which he then bound into volumes, as well as some boxes of biographical material, which Palmquist probably planned to have bound.
    The subseries also includes photocopies of works compiled or written by others about photographers or photography studios. Many volumes include material compiled by historical archaeologist Alan Roland Woolworth during his work as a research fellow at the Minnesota Historical Society.
    Dates attributed to compiled materials in this subseries reflect dates of compilation rather than the dates covered by the material in the particular volume.
    Each entry for a name in the subseries represents a single volume of general biographical notes compiled by Palmquist. Multiple entries for the same name represent multiple volumes on that individual or corporate body.
    - Abell, Frank George, Jr. (Box 44)
    - Addis, Alfred Shea (Box 45)
    - Anderson, Hugh (Box 46)
    - Anderson, Hugh (Box 47)
    - Antrim, Benajah Jay (Box 48)
    - Baker, Isaac Wallace (Box 49)
    - Banvard, John
      - Hanners, John. "The Adventures of an Artist: John Banvard (1815-1891) and his Mississippi Panorama", 1980 (Box 50)
        General note
        Thesis (Ph. D.), Michigan State University
    - Batchelder Bros. (Box 51)
    - Bayley & Brother (Box 52)
    - Beals, Henry Sherman (Box 53)
    - Bradley & Rulofson
      - Palmquist, Peter. Bradley and Rulofson Inventory of Images in the Palmquist Collection, 1991 December (Box 54)
    - Bradley, Henry William (Box 55)
    - Brewster, John Calvin (Box 56)
    - Britt, Peter (Box 57)
    - Britt, Peter (Box 58)
      - Miller, Alan Clark. "Peter Britt: Pioneer Photographer of the Siskiyous", 1972 (Box 59)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), Trinity College
    - Bromley, Edward A., compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 60)
    - Bruguiere, Peder S.
      - Photograph Formula Book, compiled by Peder S. Bruguiere, 1888-1922 (Box 61)
      - Photograph Formula Book, compiled by Peder S. Bruguiere, photocopy (Box 62)
    - Burgess, George Henry
      - Palmquist, Peter. George Henry Burgess, Miscellaneous Notes from the Collection of the Oakland Museum (Box 63)
    - Bush, Henry (Box 64)
    - Canepa, Peter Matthew (Box 65)
    - Carr, Richard (Box 66)
    - Carvalho, Solomon Nunes (Box 67)
    - Carbutt, John, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 68)
    - Carpenter, Aurelius Ormando (Box 69)
    - Coombs, Frederick C. (Box 70)
    - Coombs, Frederick C. (Box 71)
    - Coombs, Frederick C. (Box 72)
    - Curtis, Edward S.
      - Makepeace, Anne. "The Shadow Hunter: The Life and Visions of Edward S. Curtis," typescript, circa 1990 (Box 73)
        Screenplay about Edward S. Curtis
    - Dassonville, William Edward (Box 74)
    - Dassonville, William Edward (Box 75)
    - Delong, Charles Egbert (Box 76)
    - D'Estrella, Theophilus Hope (Box 77)
    - D'Heureuse, Rudolph (Box 78)
      - Duffield, Anne Q. The Mojave Road Survey Project: Historic Archaeology in the Mojave Desert, California, 1984 (Box 79)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), California State University, Fullerton
    - Dorin, George (Box 80)
    - Dossetter, Edward
      - Haas, Pamela, "Edward Dossetter," typescript (photocopy), 1980 August (Box 81)
    - E. & H. T. Anthony (Firm) (Box 82)
    - Ebell, Adrian, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 83)
    - Edgar Cherry & Company (Box 84)
    - Edgar Cherry & Company (Box 85)
    - Edgar Cherry & Company (Box 86)
    - Fardon, George Robinson (Box 87)
    - Fardon, George Robinson (Box 88)
      - Birt, Rodger C., "The Most Beautiful Views and Public Buildings of San Francisco: The Photographs of George R. Fardon," typescript (photocopy), circa 1998 (Box 89)
    - Fiske, George
      - Hickman, Paul Addison. "The Life and Photographic Works of George Fiske, 1835-1918", 1979 December (Box 90)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), Arizona State University
    - Fitzgibbon, John H., and William Fitzgibbon (Box 91)
    - Flaglor, Amasa Plummer (Box 92)
    - Ford, James May (Box 93)
    - Genthe, Arnold (Box 94)
    - Gentile, Charles (Box 95)
    - Grant, Martin Howe (Box 96)
    - Harris, W. (Box 97)
    - Hart, Alfred A. (Box 98)
      - Willumson, Glenn Gardner. "Alfred A. Hart: Photographer of the Transcontinental Railroad", 1984 (Box 99)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), University of California, Davis
    - Hazeltine, George Irving (Box 100)
    - Hazeltine, Martin Mason (Box 101)
    - Hazeltine, Martin Mason (Box 102)
    - Heller, Louis Herman (Box 103)
    - Hesler, Alexander, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 104)
    - Hillyer, Hamilton Biscoe
      - Young, William Russell. "H. B. Hillyer: Life and Career of a Nineteenth Century Texas Photographer", 1985 December (Box 105)
        Thesis (Master of Arts), University of Texas at Austin
    - Hutchings, James Mason, 1848-1855 (Box 105a)
      Photocopies of typed transcripts made by Gertrude Hutchings Mills of diaries and correspodnence of Hutchings
      Diary, 1848-1849, that records voyage from Liverpool, England to New York, and his subsequent overland journey to California from New Orleans, describing encounters with Indians and concluding with a list of names of those whose graves he found along the way
      Diary, 1855, describes travels in the mining regions of California, and in the Rogue River area of Oregon, mentioning available accommodations and anecdotes pertaining to the sites, and relating his experiences with Indians and Chinese.
      Includes "list of views" sent from Shasta to Placerville, Dec. 25, 1855, and names of towns in California in 1855
      Also includes copies of three letters, 1849-1851, concerning conditions in the mines, mainly around Placerville, California.
      Existence and Location of Originals
      Originals in the Library of Congress
    - Illingworth, William Henry, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 106)
    - Jacoby, William H., compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 107)
    - Jackson, William Henry
      - Hales, Peter B. William Henry Jackson and the Transformation of the American Landscape, typescript (photocopy), 1987 (Box 108)
      - Hales, Peter B. William Henry Jackson and the Transformation of the American Landscape, typescript (photocopy) (Box 109)
    - James, George Wharton (Box 110)
    - Johnson, Albert (Box 111)
    - Johnson, Albert (Box 112)
    - Johnson, George Howard (Box 113)
    - Johnson, Charles Wallace Jacob (Box 114)
    - Johnson, Charles Wallace Jacob (Box 115)
    - Johnson, Charles Wallace Jacob (Box 116)
    - Jones, John Wesley (Box 117)
    - Judkins, David Roby (Box 118)
    - Lawrence & Houseworth (Box 119)
    - Lawrence & Houseworth (Box 120)
    - Le Plongeon, Augustus (Box 121)
    - Lummis, Charles Fletcher (Box 122)
      - Hajicek, James Richard. "The Photography of Charles Fletcher Lummis, 1887 to 1892", 1978 (Box 123)
        Thesis (Ph. D.), University of New Mexico
    - Mills, C. C. (Box 124)
    - Mumler, William H.
      - Cloutier, Crista. Mumler's Ghosts, 2002 (Box 125)
        Screenplay about William H. Mumler.
    - Muybridge, Eadweard James (Box 126)
      - Newspaper Cuttings Book, compiled by Eadweard James Muybridge, photocopy (Box 127)
        Originals at Kingston Museum, Kingston upon Thames, United Kingdom
    - McMillan Bros. (Box 128)
    - Nahl Bros. (Box 129)
    - Norcross, Oliver H. P. (Box 130)
    - Patterson, Frank (Box 131)
    - Pierce, Charles Chester, compiled by Kathleen L. Miller (Box 132)
    - Reilly, John James (Box 133)
    - Reilly, John James (Box 134)
    - Reilly, John James (Box 135)
    - Reilly, John James (Box 136)
      - Hickman, Paul Addison. "John James Reilly, 1838-1894: Photographic Views of American Scenery", 1987 December (Box 137)
    - Rulofson, William Herman (Box 138)
    - Rulofson, William Herman (Box 139)
    - Savage, Charles Roscoe (Box 140)
    - Schumacher, Leo J. (Box 141)
    - Scripture, John Calvin (Box 142)
    - Shaw, Seth Louis (Box 143)
    - Shew, Jacob (Box 144)
    - Shew, William (Box 145)
    - Shortridge, Louis
      - Urminska, Suzanna A. "Tlingit Emulsions: The Ethnographic Photography of Louis Shortridge", 2001 (Box 146)
        Thesis (Bachelor of Arts), University of Pennsylvania
    - Spooner, John Pitcher (Box 147)
    - Stanley, John Mix (Box 148)
    - Strong, Mark Hopkins (Box 149)
    - Strong, Nathan Bixby (Box 150)
    - Strong, Wallace Kealola (Box 151)
    - Taber, Isaiah West (Box 152)
    - Thomas Houseworth & Company (Box 153)
    - Todd, John A. (Box 154)
    - Tuttle, William Nutting (Box 155)
    - Vance, Robert H.
      - Genealogical Research, 1 box (Box 156)
      - Volume 1: Research Correspondence and Squire Vance's Probate (Box 157)
      - Volume 1A: Squire Vance's Will (Box 158)
      - Volume 2: Squire Vance Notes and Information about His Life in Maine (Box 159)
      - Volume 3: The Maine and Boston Years (1825-50) (Box 160)
      - Volume 4: The South American Years (1847-50), also supplements to Volume 2 and Volume 3 (Box 161)
      - Volume 5: Vance Image Collections and Miscellaneous Illustrations (Box 162)
      - Volume 6
      - Volume 7: Miscellaneous Notes: Boston, South America, and California (Box 163)
      - Volume 8: Topical Notes, the "Lost 300" (1851), Solano County Deeds (1853-66), The Limantour Case, Vance/Weed (ca. 1858-59) and Washington territory (1873-74) (Box 164)
      - Alexander, Abel, "Robert H. Vance, Pionero del Daguerrotipo en Chile," typescript (Box 165)
    - Watkins, Carleton Eugene (Box 166)
    - Watkins, Carleton Eugene (Box 167)
    - Watkins, Carleton Eugene (Box 168)
    - Watkins, Carleton Eugene (Box 169)
      - Greenbeaux, Mary Pauline. "The Early Yosemite Photographs of Carleton E. Watkins", 1972 (Box 170)
      - Sexton, Nanette M. Carleton E. Watkins: Pioneer California Photographer, 1829-1916: a Study in the Evolution of Photographic Style During the First Decade of Wet Plate Photography, 1982 (Box 171)
        Thesis (Ph. D.), Harvard University
      - Carleton E. Watkins: Collections of Watkin's Photographs Reviewed 1980-83, compiled by Peter Palmquist and Martha Sandweiss, 1980-1983 (Box 172)
      - C. E. Watkins Photographs in the George Eastman House Collection, compiled by Sara Beckner (1985) (Box 173)
      - Carleton Emmons Watkins Photographs in the E. B. Crocker Collection at the Crocker Art Museum, 1991 August (Box 174)
        Bound with a copy of Joe William Johnson, The Early Pacific Coast Photographs of Carleton E. Watkins (Berkeley, California: Water Resources Center, University of California, 1960)
      - Loeffler, Jane C. "Landscape as Legend: Carleton E. Watkins in Kern County, California," typescript, 1991 June 3 (Box 175)
    - Weed, Charles Leander (Box 176)
    - Weed, Charles Leander (Box 177)
    - Weed, Charles Leander (Box 178)
    - Weed, Charles Leander (Box 179)
      - A. W. Hood and Mary V. Hood. "C. L. Weed: The Middle Fork of the American River: Then and Now, 1858-1958," typescript (photocopy), circa 1958 (Box 180)
    - Whitney, Joel Emmons, compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 181)
    - Zimmerman, Charles A., compiled by Alan Roland Woolworth, 1988-1995 (Box 182)
  - California Research Volumes
    Volumes are arranged under eight headings: California Photographers, California Photographers Organizations and Photography Schools, California Stereographs, Photography in San Francisco, Photography and Art in California, Photography and Art in the Yosemite Valley, Photographic Collections in California, California History, Writings of Richard Steven Street
    This subseries consists of miscellaneous notes and photocopies of secondary material chiefly about photographers, photography, art, and history in California compiled by Palmquist, which he then bound into volumes. It also includes photocopies of works compiled or written by others, which are noted in the list.
    - California Photographers
      - California Daguerrotypists, Miscellaneous Notes, 1849-1860 (Box 183)
      - California Photographers by County
        - Volume 1: Alameda County to Humboldt County, 1971-1992 (Box 184)
        - Volume 2: Humboldt County, 1971-1992 (Box 185)
        - Volume 3: Humboldt County, 1971-1992 (Box 186)
        - Volume 4: Humboldt County, 1971-1992 (Box 187)
        - Volume 5: Humboldt County to San Bernardino County, 1971-1992 (Box 188)
        - Volume 6: San Francisco County to Santa Clara County, 1971-1992 (Box 189)
        - Volume 7: Santa Clara County to Shasta County, 1971-1992 (Box 190)
        - Volume 8: Shasta County to Siskiyou County, 1971-1992 (Box 191)
        - Volume 9: Siskiyou County to Yuba County, 1971-1992 (Box 192)
      - California Photographers
        Photocopies and manuscript lists compiled by Palmquist from state, county, and city directories, as well as census records and other sources that document photographers and photography studios in California from 1850 to 1950
        - Volume A: California Photographers Miscellaneous Directory Listings, 1850-1915 (Box 193)
        - Volume B: California Photographers Miscellaneous Listings Directory and Census Listings, 1860-1920 (Box 194)
        - Volume C: California Photographers Directory Listing, Pacific Coast Business Directories, Alameda, San Francisco and Santa Clara Counties, 1867-1920 (Box 195)